Guide to the Simon W. and Sophie Gerson Papers TAM 330
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Papers, 1927-2001
  - Correspondence: Wochenpost, 1957-1975 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1931-1949 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1950-1954 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1955-1959 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1960-1969 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1970-1975 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, May 1975-Dec 1975 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Chronological, 1996-2000 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Daily Worker: Gerson Memo to CP Secretariat, Jul 7, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Daily Worker: Correspondence, etc. regarding Re-Establishment of, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Daily Worker: Crisis (Gates Resignation; Gerson becomes Editor, 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Devaney Bill (New York State Civil Service Anti-Communist Measure), 1940 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Discussion Group Proposal on Exploratory Committee on Independent Political Action, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections?, 1980-1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections? Acknowledgements and Preface, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections? Chapter on Communist Party and Ballot Rights, 1974-1984 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Do we Really have Free Elections? Chapter on Ballot Rights, 1978, 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections? Chapter on Bella Abzug (and Correspondence), 1989 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Do we Really Have Free Elections? Chapter on Constitution, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections? Chapter on Elections and 1947 Electoral Process, Undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Do we Really Have Free Elections? Chapter on "Post World War [War II] "Scare Hints, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections? Chapter on The Peoples Front, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Do We Really have Free Elections? Chapter on Who Should Vote? The Early Debates, Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections? Correspondence, 1988-1991 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Do we Really Have Free Elections? Correspondence: Mahler Institute, 1988-1995 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Do We Really Have Free Elections? Research, 1980-1990 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - 18th Avenue-Shore Parkway Block Association, 1981-1982 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - FBI Wire Tapping, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Feinberg Law Closing brief of the CP of NY (Gerson, of Counsel), Jun 17, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Felshin, Roy "Why I did Not Resign: An Open Letter to the City Planning Commission", May 6, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - The Fixer (Poem about Political Corruption), by William W. Wormer, Undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Foster, William Z. Letter to [CP] National Administration Committee re Daily Worker(Individual Criticism of Gerson position on Hungary), Aug 31, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Foster, William Z. Speech: Radio Station WMCA, Nov 2, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Gates, John "Why I Quit the Communist Party" (New York Post Reprint of six articles), 1958 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Italy Gerson trip to (PCI Festival, Modena), 1966 (Box 15, Folder 14A)
  - Hungary, 1956-1957 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Idea File (for newspaper articles), 1957 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Independent Committee for the Support of Foster and Ford, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Informers and the Smith Act, 1952-1954 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - International Organization of Journalists, 1990-1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Communists, 1982-1985 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Jury System (Includes Smith Act Materials), 1952 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Lapin, Adam. Tweedledum and Tweedledee: The American Two-Party System (typescript, 467 leaves; with Comments by SWG), Undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Liberal Party, 1944-1948 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Marcantonio, Vito: Speech (as Chair of NY County American Labor Party), Radio Station WMCA, Aug 9, 1943 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - McCarran Act, 1948-1968 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Minor, Robert: Letter to Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Sep 23, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Movement for a Democratic Society, Undated, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - New York (N.Y.) Board Of Elections: Annual Report [Gerson's annotated copy], 1937 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - New York Politics, 1975-1986 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - New York State Italian American Committee for Roosevelt, Undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Notebook: Bibliography on Labor Politics; Abzug-Moynihan 76 Race; Minnesota Farmer Labor Party, Undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Notes for Talks and Speeches, 1980-1983 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Notes for Talks and Speeches, 1983-1992 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Passport Denial [Gerson ] /Right to Travel, 1957 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - People's Weekly World: Journalistic Guidelines, Undated, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Pete: The Story of Peter V. Cacchione: Correspondence, 1974-1990 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Pete: The Story of Peter V. Cacchione: Research, Undated, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Pete: The Story of Peter V. Cacchione: Reviews, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Poland: Anti-Semitism, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Proportional Representation: "Ballad for Proportional Representation" by Milton Ost, 1947 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Proportional Representation: Research, 1947, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Proportional Representation: Research Clippings, 1938-1980 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Quotations, Undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Remarks at Funeral of Fred Breihl, Mar 14, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Rosenberg Case, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Salute to Si Gerson, Nov 20, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Samuel Greenstein, et al v. Federated Meat Corp (Jack Kranis, et al), 1948 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Simon, Will (pseud? Editor of Morning Freiheit) Clippings and Articles, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Smith Act Amnesty Campaign, Jun 1952-Mar 1960 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Smith Act Amnesty Campaign Correspondence, Dec 1957-Jun 1959 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Smith Act: Examination of Gerson, Mar 1949 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Smith Act: Families Committee, Jul 1952-Jun 1987 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Smith Act: Gerson Arrest and Acquittal Clippings, 1952 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Smith Act: Gerson Correspondence, Aug 1941-Nov 1952 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Smith Act: Gerson Memos (to National Secretariat CPUSA) etc., 1950 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Smith Act: Gerson Testimony, Aug 23, 1949 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Smith Act: Gerson Testimony in Cleveland Case, Jan 1956-Feb 1956 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Smith Act: Miscellaneous, 1950-1960 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Smith Act: Record of Cases (By Gerson), Oct 1956 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Smith Act: Right of Counsel (Correspondence, memos, etc), Sep 1951-Aug 1955 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Smith Act: U.S. vs. Flynn Clippings, Feb 1952-Jun 1952 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Smith Act: U.S. vs. Flynn Correspondence and Documents., Dec 1950-Oct 1957 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Smith Act: Writings (as evidence, etc.), Feb 1938-Jun 1982 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - The Smiths (poem/lyric) by Marty Garaway re: Smith Act, Undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Society of Silurians (New York Journalists Organization), 1983-1998 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Speech: Cornell University, 1955 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Speech: Rutgers University, Mar 10, 1949 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Speech: Tribute to a Workings Class Journalist (Harry Raymond aka Harold J. Lightcap), 1959 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Speech: Yale University, Oct 1952-Dec 1952 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1939-1994 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Stachel, Jack "On the History of CPUSA" Lecture, Jun 1965 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Student Material (Gerson) George Washington H.S., City College, 1925-1928, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Gerson Testimony before House Committee on Un-American Activities, May 2, 1950 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Third Parties: Speech at Jefferson Forum (Feb.20, 1955) w/Jack McManus: Clippings, Notes, Dec 1954-Aug 1956 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Thompson, Robert, 1943-1966 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Travel: Bulgaria, etc, 1970-1978 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Travel: Portugal, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Travel: Soviet Union, 1975, 1977 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Third Parties Research Notes [5x8 cards], undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Trip to Soviet Union, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Armed Forces: Gerson's WWII Service, 1940-1997 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Armed Forces: GI Newspapers, 1944-1945 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Wheeler, Tim: Report re Alleged Theft of Peoples Weekly World Materials by Carl Bloice & Barry Cohen, Jan 24, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Writings about Gerson, 1952-1989 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Writings (as Festus Gunn): "Nikita Sergeyevich in the Unites States", 1959 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Writings (as Will Melvin), 1958-1959 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Writings: Book Reviews, Nov 1956-Jun 1991 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Writings: "Does Nader Candidacy Help the Right Wing?", 1996 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Writings: Manuscript/Typescript [Published/Unpublished], Apr 1957-Nov 1997 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Writings: New Masses, 1946-1947 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Writings: Other Newspapers (not Daily Worker, Peoples Daily World, Peoples Weekly World), May 1972-Nov 1995 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Writings: Peoples Daily/Weekly World, 1955-1998 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Writings, Published: Pamphlets & Journal Articles, Feb 1944-Jan 1993 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Writings: Synopsis and Outline: Labor and Politics, ca.1938-1939 (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Series II: Scrapbooks, undated
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Series III: Photographs, 1927-1991
  - American Student Council Delegation to Russia, 1927 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Cacchione, Peter V., 1943-1945; undated (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: Funeral Album, 1947 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Gerson, Simon, 1970-1991 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Gerson, Simon: City Council Campaign, 1948 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Graphics (Oversize), 1938 (Box OS003, Folder 1)
  - Graphics (Published), undated (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Marcantonio, Vito and Simon Gerson, 1948 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - PCI Festical (Modena, Italy), 1966 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Postcard: "Class War Prisoners", undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Loose photographs and negatives, 1944-1994 (Box 32, Folder 11-17)
- Series IV: Addendum, 1918-1947; undated
  - Clippings, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Labor and Politics": Research Notes, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - "Labor and Politics": Typescript, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Proportional Representation: Clippings, etc., 1947 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - "A Serious Problem" (re: Catholic education, by Joseph V. McKee), undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Writings, Miscellaneous (Gerson), undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Unprocessed, undated (Box 27)
- Series V: Addendum 2011 (Unprocessed), undated
  - Papers, Miscellaneous: Campaigns for office and other political activities (printed ephemera, clippings, correspondence); birthday celebrations and other biographical materials, undated (Box 28)
  - Papers, Miscellaneous: Campaigns for office and other political activities (printed ephemera, clippings, correspondence); birthday celebrations and other biographical materials, undated (Box 29)
  - Oversized and Miscellaneous items: Clippings (including Sophie Gerson/Gastonia); a 1948 campaign speech by Gerson on two records; a videocassette from an 80th birthday celebration for SG; buttons; a rolled high school certificate from 1925, several rolled clippings and posters, undated (Box 30)
  - Audio (cassettes and reel to reel tapes): include SG, Gus Hall Updates, undated (Box 31)